<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A mirrour to all that loue to follow the warres go trudge my little booke, possesse ech willing hand, and giue all leaue to looke, that seekes to vnderstand, the trauels of thy knight, plead hard to hold his right, who finds thee may be bould, his actions to vnfould.</title>
            <author>I. B.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1589</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 20 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00290</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1041.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1050</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">20007575</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 20007575</idno>
            <idno type="VID">23600</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00290)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 23600)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1719:28)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A mirrour to all that loue to follow the warres go trudge my little booke, possesse ech willing hand, and giue all leaue to looke, that seekes to vnderstand, the trauels of thy knight, plead hard to hold his right, who finds thee may be bould, his actions to vnfould.</title>
                  <author>I. B.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Woolfe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1589.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: I.B.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴ (last two leaves blank).</note>
                  <note>"A poem on Peregrine Bertie, Baron Willoughby de Eresby"--STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bertie, Peregrine, --  Sir.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Elizabeth, 1558-1603.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:23600:1"/>
            <p>A Mirrour to all that loue to follow the warres.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Go trudge my little booke,</l>
               <l>Poſſeſſe ech willing hand,</l>
               <l>And giue all leaue to looke,</l>
               <l>That ſeekes to vnderſtand,</l>
               <l>The trauels of thy Knight,</l>
               <l>Plead hard to hold his right:</l>
               <l>Who finds thee may be bould,</l>
               <l>His actions to vnfould.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by Iohn Woolfe, 1589.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:23600:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of St George on horseback killing the dragon</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:23600:2"/>
            <head>To the honorable minded Souldier.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe late frostie mornings (pleaſing my humor) rouſed me ſooner (then of cuſtome) from my drowſie bedde, and with deſire (preſsing me) I went abroad to walke.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Where all alone, betrampling froſned ground,</l>
               <l>Me thought to heare, ſome fierce and warlike ſound:</l>
               <l>For <hi>Phoebus</hi> then began his courſe in skies,</l>
               <l>On rolling wheeles, his fierie wagon flies,</l>
               <l>Moſt ſwift, to ſend blacke <hi>Pluto</hi> to his bed:</l>
               <l>Who giuing place, left skie like blood as red.</l>
            </q>
            <p>This made me conceiue ſome diſcourſe within my ſelfe, and wondering much, there came vnto mind, how God had pleaſed to bleſſe, and keepe our Queene, and land from the thundering and tempeſtious ſtormes of all our mortall, and furious enimies: with this conceit my ioy was much augmented, and did amaſe me greatlie to conſider, how far from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon expectation, the late rumors of wars, and the rage of thoſe which wrought to deſtroy vs, were blowne ouer and gone from vs (with their owne confuſion:) and we inreſt ſtill liuing (in all felicitie) ruled, and gouerned by <hi>Elizabeth</hi> our moſt bleſſed, and redoubled Princes. This ſeemed to my wonder moſt maruellous, and more moued me to muſe, when ſtepping on a peece of broken Ice, I ſpurned forth a paper (rolled vp,) wherein when I had opened and read, appeared matter ſitting my preſent deuiſe: which noting, by what chance and fortune, and in what ſeaſon it came to my hands, ſodenly reſolued to haue it printed: yet not willing to be ouer raſh in preſenting vnto your viewes, what I knew not aſſuredly true, found after occaſion of conference, with ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie of good iudgement, who I knew had long frequented the Low countries (from whence they lately came) By whom vnder ſtanding all
<pb facs="tcp:23600:3"/>was most true, and that they added much more honor vnto the Lorde Willughbie, (her Maiesties Lieutenant generall) whome this booke toucheth: I greatly longed (although I neuer did ſee his Lordſhips per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) to haue his ſo noble indeuours (with all ſpeed) publiſhed: which as it may worthelie be placed for a looking glaſſe, to ſuch as woulde game fame, and honor: So with your good fauor and patience, I will be bould to name this ſhort diſcourſe, <hi>A Mirrour to all that loue to follow the warres:</hi> Whereby if any ſhall take profite (in imitating his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips ſo honorable deſire) to purchaſe Englands good, it will aduance him, and his to a neuer ending fame. And our ſacred Prince (by whom we liue moſt happie) ſhall reape ſweete comfort (in her ſo bleſſed daies) when her floriſhing realme ſhalbe garniſhed, and ſtored with many ſuch Lord Willughbies; who leaueth not both day and night to liue in rest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe toile and trauell, and ioyeth moſt when newes is brought, or meanes found, how hee may beſt ſpoile or incounter her Maiesties enemies. This onely do I craue, that with good conſtruction you will (with fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor) reade what followeth, and yeelde but due right, where nought beſides is demanded: and when by chance I finde the like of any one of you, I promiſe to performe as much, (and more) if ſo your actions me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, or deſerue.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in a greater matter at command, <hi>R. B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="acrostic">
            <pb facs="tcp:23600:3"/>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <label>P</label> Praiſe worthie yeald to Mars his noble knight,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>E</label> Excellent fame, in world ſhines paſſing bright,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>R</label> Reporting ſtill his valiant actes and deedes,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>E</label> Engraued be his name, ſo well he ſpeedes,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>G</label> Gould is too baſe, his actions of more price,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>R</label> Regiſtred are in hearts, by warres right happie thrice,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>I</label> In bleſſed time his life, did nature frame,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>N</label> None knowes his deedes, but will confeſſe the ſame,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>E</label> Except they hate, no man dare wrong his name.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <label>L</label> Lord by diſcent, the honour of his houſe</l>
               <l>
                  <label>O</label> O comfort great, to each good Engliſh hart,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>R</label> Reioyce, be glad, for now your noble men,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>D</label> Diſdaines no toyle, nor flies from painefull ſmart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <label>W</label> Will any man denie, that he is wiſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>I</label> I thinke not one mo good actes doth deuiſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>L</label> Let him ſtand vp, when honour bids him riſe:</l>
               <l>
                  <label>L</label> Let him ſaid I, nay ſure he can not fall,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>V</label> Vpright he ſtandes, whom valiant all men call,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>G</label> Giue him then duly right, that honored is of all,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>H</label> Heape ſhame on ſuch, as wiſh thee ill to ſpeede,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>B</label> By courage ſtout, make Princes foes ſtill bleede,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>Y</label> Your God, &amp; Queene, will recompence indeed.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:23600:4"/>
            <head>A Mirror for Souldiers.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THoſe which in ought do well, deſeru's ſome praiſe to gaine,</l>
               <l>Yet not ſo much by farre, moſt will preſume to thinke,</l>
               <l>As he which ſtill ſuſtaines, a world of endleſſe paine,</l>
               <l>And that from taske him ſet, no toyle can force to ſhrinke:</l>
               <l>Then yeeld him duly right, whom fame with trump co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mends,</l>
               <l>That wiſely, and with care, his countries cauſe defendes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For learned and diſcret, moſt men do know him well,</l>
               <l>That he is wiſe, and iuſt, report hath ſpred the ſame,</l>
               <l>His actions, and deſertes, no leſſe abroad can tell,</l>
               <l>He ſerues, and feares high Ioue: And reuerenceth his name:</l>
               <l>His wit, his will, applyed, his learned skill, and all,</l>
               <l>That nought but happie hap, to Englandes cauſe might fall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>His gallant Sprit appeard, when young to Daniſh king,</l>
               <l>Was ſent Ambaſſadour, from our moſt Royall Queene,</l>
               <l>How grauely he declarde, and anſwere backe did bring</l>
               <l>To truſt repoſde in him, Not better hath beene ſeene</l>
               <l>Such care of common cauſe, did rule his liberall minde,</l>
               <l>As king, and people there, moſt louing he doth finde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Since he beganne to beare, the <hi>Martiall</hi> pearcing Lance,</l>
               <l>And to the warres to bende, his well addicted will,</l>
               <l>Himſelfe before his men, he euer doth aduance,</l>
               <l>With courage preſt to fight, their mindes with ioy to fill:</l>
               <l>His worthie heart vpſtird, Soone breakes their braueſt troup,</l>
               <l>And Princes rightfull cauſe, makes all her foes to ſtoupe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He chaſeth them in feare, like Lion fierce with rage,</l>
               <l>And leaues not off purſute, till all are pulled downe,</l>
               <l>His courage makes him oft, himſelfe midſt them enrage,</l>
               <l>And ſuffereth nought vnſought, to get or winne renowne:</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Willughbie</hi> (in right) Lord worthie of great prayſe,</l>
               <l>For Countries cauſe maintainde, liues happie in theſe dayes.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:23600:4"/>
            <lg>
               <l>How many men of <hi>Rome,</hi> And of the Grekiſh rout,</l>
               <l>Had beene forgot (now dead) And ſmothered with the graue,</l>
               <l>Of other Nations eke, (that valiant were and ſtout,</l>
               <l>If whilſt they liu'd ſome friend, their actions would not ſaue:</l>
               <l>Or write them ſtraight in bookes, as now this noble knight,</l>
               <l>(For yeelding Countries due) deſerueth in his right.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What man hath <hi>Parma</hi> found, in all this fower yeares warre,</l>
               <l>More preſt with will (then he) To meete him in the face,</l>
               <l>With paine hath he not ſought, to finde him neere and farre,</l>
               <l>And often ſpoyld his men, with foule, and much diſgrace:</l>
               <l>He marcheth on with cheare, his friend Fortune doth ſtand,</l>
               <l>And toyles like him that hath, his Princes cauſe in hande.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>At <hi>Zutphen</hi> when the Duke, came to relieue the place,</l>
               <l>This worthie <hi>Willughbie,</hi> did ſerue right well that day,</l>
               <l>and ſurely mounted there, with gallant comely grace,</l>
               <l>Firſt brake his launce, and then, with ſword he made his way:</l>
               <l>Emidſt his foes in place, And did beſtirre him ſo,</l>
               <l>As he whom Countries cauſe, made deſperate on to go.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He paſſed on ſo farre, As all beganne to dread,</l>
               <l>If God bleſt him not well, he would be take or ſlaine,</l>
               <l>His Baſſes puld away, his plumes cut from his head,</l>
               <l>His Armes broke with blowes: yet ſafe returned againe:</l>
               <l>He <hi>Cariſcio</hi> tooke, And priſoner brought away,</l>
               <l>So iuſt was Countries cauſe, that no man could him ſtay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No Conuoie could eſcape, From his victorious hande,</l>
               <l>Nor enemie durſt approch, nor come before the towne,</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Burgen</hi> whileſt he rulde, And gouernour did ſtande,</l>
               <l>They doubted then ſo much, his greatneſſe of renowne:</l>
               <l>The garriſon him lou'd, and honored him in heart,</l>
               <l>For Princes cauſe and them, he could indure much ſmart.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:23600:5"/>
            <lg>
               <l>His Challenge nobly made, oft times to braueſt foe,</l>
               <l>Declarde a courage ſtout, diſpiſing cowardiſe:</l>
               <l>He dared to the fight, (the letters yet to ſhowe,)</l>
               <l>of <hi>Guaſt Marquis</hi> right, that valiant was and wiſe:</l>
               <l>But he refuſde to cope, with him moſt worthie knight,</l>
               <l>Who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> countries cauſe made ſtrong, &amp; doubl'd force &amp; might.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When th'erle of Leyceſter, by Princes ſtraight beheſt,</l>
               <l>For England ſhould returne, And leaue thoſe watres and toyle,</l>
               <l>Lorde Willughbie (as fit) in honour eke the beſt,</l>
               <l>Which on that ſide remainde, was thruſt therein to moyle:</l>
               <l>His good indeuours paſt, to further Countries right,</l>
               <l>Made him ſoone to deſerue, fauor of euerie wight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Confirmed then in place, He entred ſtraight in care,</l>
               <l>And with vpright reſpect, regarding his great charge,</l>
               <l>To end all troubles firſt, no trauell he did ſpare,</l>
               <l>Thoſe Countries were in picke, and furie went at large:</l>
               <l>But ſuch a courſe he tooke, the peoples heartes to gaine,</l>
               <l>To fauour common cauſe, toyle was to him no paine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Commons were at ſtrife, great diſcord did appeare,</l>
               <l>Ech towne diuided was, one Prouince other hate,</l>
               <l>To Armes they runne amayn, the helme fierce wrath then ſtird,</l>
               <l>Ech thirſt for others bloud, ſuch was their heauie ſtate:</l>
               <l>But he by graue foreſight, brake all this franticke fit,</l>
               <l>And ſeekes for Countries good, their humors for to hit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When States enſconſed round, the towne of <hi>Medinblicke,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Count Maurice</hi> ioynd with them, In hope poore <hi>Snoy</hi> to ſpoyle,</l>
               <l>Such mallice rulde their braines, as none had ſeene the like,</l>
               <l>And for to winne the ſame, they kept a maruellous coyle:</l>
               <l>Till they with paine and coſt, by this braue Lorde ſuſtainde,</l>
               <l>(For Countries cauſe in chiefe) to peace &amp; loue were gainde.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:23600:5"/>
            <lg>
               <l>When <hi>Gertruidenberge,</hi> in mutinie diſcontent,</l>
               <l>Put <hi>Hollocke</hi> foorth their gates, with him the Captaines all,</l>
               <l>Not dreading Count, nor States, for deſperate all were bent,</l>
               <l>To yeeld themſelues and towne, And to the foe to fall:</l>
               <l>The States in feare beſought, Count <hi>Maurice</hi> then did pray,</l>
               <l>For Countries common good, that he would worke a ſtay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Wherein, though hard it ſeemd, to ſtoppe ſo mad a will,</l>
               <l>From working ſome outrage, in hazard of the place,</l>
               <l>Which for to gaine, the foe, lay preſſing on them ſtill,</l>
               <l>Not ſparing crownes, nor golde, to purchaſe ſuch a grace:</l>
               <l>Yet found this noble Lorde, ſuch meanes as ſaued all,</l>
               <l>And for his Countries cauſe, wrought to his will their fall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Him gouernour they make, Th'ingliſh Croſſe they beare,</l>
               <l>And Engliſh Captaines take, to leade there horſe and foote,</l>
               <l>They chaſt th'italian troup, of launces, who for feare,</l>
               <l>Fled to <hi>Breda</hi> amayne, his Lordſhip made them ſtoope:</l>
               <l>And though he did but walke, vnarmed out of towne,</l>
               <l>Yet zeale for Countries cauſe, them bloudie left on ground</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When <hi>Parma</hi> preſt to meete, the Spaniſh fleete at ſeas,</l>
               <l>Lay houering at <hi>Dunkerke,</hi> with fortie thouſande men,</l>
               <l>In purpoſe to inuade, and England take with eaſe,</l>
               <l>This lorde then well preparde, was readie (euen then)</l>
               <l>To take the ſeas in hope, to meete him on the way,</l>
               <l>And for his Countries cauſe, reſolu'd to force him ſtay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But when the <hi>Dukes</hi> great bragges, to ſmoke and wind did turne,</l>
               <l>And when his hope had failde, and ſpaniſh fleete was gone,</l>
               <l>He bended all his power, to <hi>Bargen</hi> faſt they runne,</l>
               <l>And gainſt that town he makes, his chiefeſt force and head:</l>
               <l>Thirtie thouſande at leaſt, his armie did containe,</l>
               <l>Yet for our Countries cauſe, our men them do diſdaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>At firſt approch when he, did thinke to view the towne,</l>
               <l>With cannon from the wall, amaſde was made to ſtand,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:23600:6"/>
               <l>The generall did ſhoot, two pages fell to ground,</l>
               <l>Starke dead, ſuch happie lucke, went with his noble hand,</l>
               <l>Then ſallied brauely foorth, at <hi>Steunberge</hi> port our men,</l>
               <l>And for their Countries cauſe, the foe they further ſend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No day almoſt did paſſe, but horſe, or foote went out,</l>
               <l>And skirmiſh braue with foe, to Englandes honour great,</l>
               <l>Themſelues confeſt our men, to be both bolde and ſtout,</l>
               <l>And paſſing fierce (they ſayde) if ſtirred vp to heate:</l>
               <l>This noble Lorde went foorth, as formoſt as the beſt,</l>
               <l>His zeale for Countries cauſe, eclipſt his ſleepe and reſt,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And though the towne was weake, vnfurniſht for defence,</l>
               <l>When <hi>Parma</hi> firſt approcht, and workes but new begunne,</l>
               <l>And though the common voice, was he would neuer thence,</l>
               <l>Vntill he tooke the ſame, no meanes his rage could ſhunne:</l>
               <l>Yet ſo beſtird all men, with wils to ſaue the place,</l>
               <l>As care for common cauſe, made him part with diſgrace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet lay he at that 'that ſiedge, encamped on three ſides,</l>
               <l>Ten or eleuen weekes, his trenches brought harde by,</l>
               <l>Not full Calliuer ſhot, wherein his men abides,</l>
               <l>And vantage for to get, in them they cloſe did lye,</l>
               <l>But all in vaine they ſpedde, their trenches ſeru'd for graue,</l>
               <l>For countries common cauſe, our men would not them ſaue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But when his hope (by force) to take the towne was fled,</l>
               <l>And that his paines and men, he dayly there had loſt,</l>
               <l>With coyne he thought corrupt, braue Grimſton, &amp; Red-head,</l>
               <l>Falſe Sligo, Simon was, his life the practiſe coſt:</l>
               <l>The North ſconce by deuice, or force they thinke to take,</l>
               <l>But zeale for Countries cauſe, their hearts enforſt to ake.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Eight hundred men were ſlaine, and drowned with the tide,</l>
               <l>For ſeeing themſelues deceiued, with force they ſtraight aſſaile,</l>
               <l>Downe falles the <hi>Palliſad,</hi> and long at ſault they bide,</l>
               <l>But twice put to retire, their purpoſe thus did faile:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:23600:6"/>
               <l>Lord Willughbie himſelfe, with Ruſſell did defend,</l>
               <l>And for our Princes cauſe, their force againſt them bend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus their deuiſe did proue, a plot their throats to cut,</l>
               <l>For they by graue foreſight, were drawen to the ſpoyle,</l>
               <l>By Grimſtone reſolute, who forth of ſconce was put,</l>
               <l>To lead them on like ſheepe, vnto this deadly foyle:</l>
               <l>Where you may view deceipt, caught faſt in his owne net,</l>
               <l>For common zeale, and cauſe, their diueliſh plot did let.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I wiſh no better happe, in treaſon may ſucceed,</l>
               <l>Then many yeares haue chanſt, To men of curſed minds,</l>
               <l>Which ſought by ſpightfull drifts, in purpoſe for to ſpeed,</l>
               <l>As <hi>Sligo</hi> did, but all, too late repentance finds,</l>
               <l>Feare nought their treaſons then, let courage buckler be,</l>
               <l>And in your countries cauſe, their heart bloud you ſhall ſee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Here may you ſee the works of mightie Ioue aboue,</l>
               <l>Here may you eke behold, that foes build in the ſand,</l>
               <l>God will defend vs ſtill, his people he will ſaue,</l>
               <l>And gainſt all furious fiends, will fight with ſtrongeſt hand,</l>
               <l>Who will not then reioyce, when wiſh ſucceeds to will,</l>
               <l>And when their countries good, doth grow, and proſper ſtill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Would god our chiefeſt men, And men poſſeſt with welth,</l>
               <l>Could frame their minds &amp; meanes, as Willughbie hath done,</l>
               <l>To ſeeke to gaine renowne, by working countries helth,</l>
               <l>And ſome frequented toiles, would thereby leaue and ſhunne:</l>
               <l>Then plentie of our foes, to England ſoone would ſeeke,</l>
               <l>With honor to our cauſe, for mercie at our feete.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I meane not here ſuch men, which countries cauſe do loue,</l>
               <l>Nor thoſe will ſeeme to blame, which haue no meanes, to will,</l>
               <l>From theſe and ſuch as ſerue, my thoughts I farre remoue,</l>
               <l>And gainſt the reſt, which might, with plaints their eares Ile fil,</l>
               <l>And crie, and call amaine, Let common cauſe in right,</l>
               <l>Be ſtill reſpected deere, and pretious in your ſight.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:23600:7"/>
            <lg>
               <l>We ſee the <hi>Pope</hi> procures, great Princes vs moleſt,</l>
               <l>We ſee what armies huge, are raiſde againſt our Queene,</l>
               <l>We ſee how ſafe we are, when ech will do his beſt,</l>
               <l>And our good God for vs, moſt ſtrong hath ſtill beene ſeene:</l>
               <l>Let all then courage take, Of what ſort or degree,</l>
               <l>Our countries cauſe is iuſt, by proofe our foes may ſee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Our <hi>Princes</hi> ſacred power, anointed from aboue,</l>
               <l>With harts, with hands, with liues, and with our deareſt blood,</l>
               <l>Shall ſtill maintained be, The people feare and loue,</l>
               <l>Let him in ſorrow dwell, that would her not much good:</l>
               <l>Long happie haue we liued, in her moſt bleſſed daies,</l>
               <l>Her care for ſubiects all, hath much aduanſt her praiſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Moſt mightie <hi>Ioue,</hi> who rules, and guides ech liuing thing,</l>
               <l>And that from higheſt throne, doſt keepe, and bleſſe our Queene</l>
               <l>Protect, defend her right, Shame and deſtruction bring,</l>
               <l>Vpon her cruell foes, and grant it may be ſeene.</l>
               <l>Throughout the world (O God) that thy ſtrong ſtretched arme</l>
               <l>Herſelfe, her cauſe, and land, preſerues from hurt or harme.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>THis knight deſerues much more, then heere I write,</l>
               <l>My verſe ſo blunt, at full, cannot recite,</l>
               <l>His wiſe and worthie acts, what fault you finde,</l>
               <l>Excuſe the ſame in me, and me you binde,</l>
               <l>A friend (in power though ſmall,) this grace yet giue</l>
               <l>Lord Willughbies deſeru'd good fame may liue;</l>
               <l>Whoſe deeds his ſecret friend, would not leaue dead,</l>
               <l>which done farewell; Ile go to hide my head,</l>
               <l>Yet ere I flie, your pardons gentlie giue,</l>
               <l>And then I hope from ſhame abrode to liue.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <closer>
               <signed>I. B.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:23600:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:23600:8"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:23600:8"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
